A Guide to the Claire Rufer-Eckmann Architectural Collection, 1928-1935, 1952, 1958
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Claire Rufer-Eckmann Architectural Collection, 1928-1935, 1952, 1958
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1998-018
3.1 cu. ft. 1 box, 6 oversize folders
Claire Rufer-Eckmann (1914-1974). Architect of Bern, Switzerland. Collection consists of architecture class notes taken by Rufer-Eckmann at l'École Polytechnique Federale de Zurich, 1928-1935, original sketches and a report on her travels in Sweden and Finland in the late 1930s, and over forty working drawings created by her as part of SAFFA 58, an exhibition of women's roles in Switzerland.
Rufer-Eckmann, Claire
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Claire Rufer-Eckmann Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in 1998.
Biographical Information
Claire Rufer-Eckmann (1914-1974) was born in Wabern, Switzerland and died in Bern. Before receiving her architecture degree in 1937, Rufer-Eckmann traveled to Sweden and Finland, studying under Gunnar Asplund and Alvar Aalto. She returned to Sweden in 1938 and lived there for two years eventually writing an unpublished report on her travels to Sweden and its architecture illustrated with ink drawings of plans and views of important buildings (present in collection).
1942 saw her return to Bern where she began to work with her husband Oskar Rufer, a developer and architect. They remained in practice together for 34 years. Their firm handled a wide variety of projects from shopping centers, theaters, schools, residential, and factories. Rufer-Eckmann specialized in design while her husband concentrated on management and development. Oskar Rufer closed the office upon Claire's death in 1974.
Rufer-Eckmann also participated in SAFFA 58 (The Swiss Exhibition for Women's Work) an exhibition held in Zurich, that focused on "women in the family, occupation and state." These exhibitions were organized and produced entirely by women and the exhibition buildings for SAFFA 58 were designed and built by Swiss women architects.
Scope and Content
The collection contains student notes from her studies at l'Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Zurich, notes and original drawings from her travels in Sweden and Finland, and several oversize folders containing 46 architectural drawings: designs of 2 pavilions for SAFFA 58, 2 drawings of Chalet Meleria in Valmont, a large drawing of Zurich, and 10 pages of accompanying notes.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
See also SAFFA 58 Architectural Drawings, 1958.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Architects--Switzerland; Architectural drawing--20th century.
Local Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Contents List
- Class notes taken by Eckmann at the ETH-Zurich, while a student: Baustatik 1 [Structural Analysis], 1928-1933. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Class notes taken by Eckmann at the ETH-Zurich, while a student: Hochbau in Stahl [Building in steel], 1935 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Class notes taken by Echmann at the ETH-Zurich, while a student: Hochbau in Eisenbeton [Construction of reinforced concrete], 1935. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Notes taken by Eckmann at the ETH-Zurich, while a student: Hochbau in Holz [Building in wood], 1935. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Notes taken by Echmann at the ETH-Zurich, while a student. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Notes from studies and travels to Sweden and Finland. Original drawings. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Architectural drawings, drawings for SAFFA 58, 1958. (Oversize Map-case 7/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
- Architectural drawings, drawings for SAFFA 58, 1958. (Oversize Map-case 7/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
- Architectural drawings, drawings for SAFFA 58, 1958. (Oversize Map-case 7/Drawer 2/Folder 3)
- Architectural drawings, drawings for SAFFA 58, 1958. (Oversize Map-case 7/Drawer 2/Folder 4)
- Architectural drawings, drawings for SAFFA 58, 1958. (Oversize Map-case 7/Drawer 2/Folder 5)
- Architectural drawings, Stadt Zurich, Chalet Meleria, SAFFA 58 drawings, 1952; 1958. (Oversize Map-case 7/Drawer 2/Folder 6)